How do you make a mountain bike for your arms that doesn't have the mountain bike cost and complexity? So as is the case with simple solutions, oftentimes the answer is right in front of your face, and for us it was levers. We use levers all the time, in tools, doorknobs, bicycle parts. And that moment of inspiration, that key invention moment, was when I was sitting in front of my design notebook and I started thinking about somebody grabbing a lever, and if they grab near the end of the lever, they can get an effectively long lever and produce a lot of torque as they push back and forth, and effectively get a low gear. And as they slide their hand down the lever, they can push with a smaller effective lever length, but push through a bigger angle every stroke, which makes a faster rotational speed, and gives you an effective high gear. So what's exciting about this system is that it's really, really mechanically simple, and you could make it using technology that's been around for hundreds of years. So seeing this in practice, this is the Leveraged Freedom Chair that, after a few years of development, we're now going into production with, and this is a full-time wheelchair user -- he's paralyzed -- in Guatemala, and you see he's able to traverse pretty rough terrain. Again, the key innovation of this technology is that when he wants to go fast, he just grabs the levers near the pivots and goes through a big angle every stroke, and as the going gets tougher, he just slides his hands up the levers, creates more torque, and kind of bench-presses his way out of trouble through the rough terrain. Now the big, important point here is that the person is the complex machine in this system. It's the person that's sliding his hands up and down the levers, so the mechanism itself can be very simple and composed of bicycle parts you can get anywhere in the world. Because those bicycle parts are so ubiquitously available, they're super-cheap. They're made by the gazillions in China and India, and we can source them anywhere in the world, build the chair anywhere, and most importantly repair it, even out in a village with a local bicycle mechanic who has local tools, knowledge and parts available. Now, when you want to use the LFC indoors, all you have to do is pull the levers out of the drivetrain, stow them in the frame, and it converts into a normal wheelchair that you can use just like any other normal wheelchair, and we sized it like a normal wheelchair, so it's narrow enough to fit through a standard doorway, it's low enough to fit under a table, and it's small and maneuverable enough to fit in a bathroom and this is important so the user can get up close to a toilet, and be able to transfer off just like he could in a normal wheelchair. Now, there's three important points that I want to stress that I think really hit home in this project. The first is that this product works well because we were effectively able to combine rigorous engineering science and analysis with user-centered design focused on the social and usage and economic factors important to wheelchair users in the developing countries. So I'm an academic at MIT, and I'm a mechanical engineer, so I can do things like look at the type of terrain you want to travel on, and figure out how much resistance it should impose, look at the parts we have available and mix and match them to figure out what sort of gear trains we can use, and then look at the power and force you can get out of your upper body to analyze how fast you should be able to go in this chair as you put your arms up and down the levers. So as a wet-behind-the-ears student, excited, our team made a prototype, brought that prototype to Tanzania, Kenya and Vietnam in 2008, and found it was terrible because we didn't get enough input from users. So because we tested it with wheelchair users, with wheelchair manufacturers, we got that feedback from them, not just articulating their problems, but articulating their solutions, and worked together to go back to the drawing board and make a new design, which we brought back to East Africa in '09 that worked a lot better than a normal wheelchair on rough terrain, but it still didn't work well indoors because it was too big, it was heavy, it was hard to move around, so again with that user feedback, we went back to the drawing board, came up with a better design, 20 pounds lighter, as narrow as a regular wheelchair, tested that in a field trial in Guatemala, and that advanced the product to the point where we have now that it's going into production. Now also being engineering scientists, we were able to quantify the performance benefits of the Leveraged Freedom Chair, so here are some shots of our trial in Guatemala where we tested the LFC on village terrain, and tested people's biomechanical outputs, their oxygen consumption, how fast they go, how much power they're putting out, both in their regular wheelchairs and using the LFC, and we found that the LFC is about 80 percent faster going on these terrains than a normal wheelchair. It's also about 40 percent more efficient than a regular wheelchair, and because of the mechanical advantage you get from the levers, you can produce 50 percent higher torque and really muscle your way through the really, really rough terrain. Now the second lesson that we learned in this is that the constraints on this design really push the innovation, because we had to hit such a low price point, because we had to make a device that could travel on many, many types of terrain but still be usable indoors, and be simple enough to repair, we ended up with a fundamentally new product, a new product that is an innovation in a space that really hasn't changed in a hundred years. And these are all merits that are not just good in the developing world. Why not in countries like the U.S. too? So we teamed up with Continuum, a local product design firm here in Boston to make the high-end version, the developed world version, that we'll probably sell primarily in the U.S. and Europe, but to higher-income buyers. And the final point I want to make is that I think this project worked well because we engaged all the stakeholders that buy into this project and are important to consider in bringing the technology from inception of an idea through innovation, validation, commercialization and dissemination, and that cycle has to start and end with end users. These are the people that define the requirements of the technology, and these are the people that have to give the thumbs-up at the end, and say, "Yeah, it actually works. It meets our needs." So people like me in the academic space, we can do things like innovate and analyze and test, create data and make bench-level prototypes, but how do you get that bench-level prototype to commercialization? So we need gap-fillers like Continuum that can work on commercializing, and we started a whole NGO to bring our chair to market -- Global Research Innovation Technology -- and then we also teamed up with a big manufacturer in India, Pinnacle Industries, that's tooled up now to make 500 chairs a month and will make the first batch of 200 next month, which will be delivered in India. And then finally, to get this out to the people in scale, we teamed up with the largest disability organization in the world, Jaipur Foot. Now what's powerful about this model is when you bring together all these stakeholders that represent each link in the chain from inception of an idea all the way to implementation in the field, that's where the magic happens. That's where you can take a guy like me, an academic, but analyze and test and create a new technology and quantitatively determine how much better the performance is. You can connect with stakeholders like the manufacturers and talk with them face-to-face and leverage their local knowledge of manufacturing practices and their clients and combine that knowledge with our engineering knowledge to create something greater than either of us could have done alone. And then you can also engage the end user in the design process, and not just ask him what he needs, but ask him how he thinks it can be achieved. And this picture was taken in India in our last field trial, where we had a 90-percent adoption rate where people switched to using our Leveraged Freedom Chair over their normal wheelchair, and this picture specifically is of Ashok, and Ashok had a spinal injury when he fell out of a tree, and he had been working at a tailor, but once he was injured he wasn't able to transport himself from his house over a kilometer to his shop in his normal wheelchair. The road was too rough. But the day after he got an LFC, he hopped in it, rode that kilometer, opened up his shop and soon after landed a contract to make school uniforms and started making money, started providing for his family again. Ashok: You also encouraged me to work. I rested for a day at home. The next day I went to my shop. Now everything is back to normal. Amos Winter: And thank you very much for having me today. (Applause)
¿Como construir una bicicleta de montaña para los brazos que no tenga su coste ni complejidad? Como sucede con las soluciones simples, a menudo la respuesta es evidente y para nosotros fue la palanca. Usamos palancas continuamente, en herramientas, pomos, y piezas de bicicleta. El momento de inspiración, el momento clave de la creación fue sentado frente a mi cuaderno de diseño cuando comencé a pensar sobre alguien sujetando una palanca. Si se sostiene cerca del final de la misma se obtiene una palanca de gran longitud que produce un gran torque según se impulsa de un lado a otro, obteniendo una marcha corta. A medida que se desliza la mano hacia abajo, se impulsa con una longitud de palanca eficaz más pequeña, pero a través de un angulo mayor, cada impulso crea una mayor velocidad de rotación y proporciona una marcha más larga. Lo emocionante de este sistema radica en que es mecánicamente muy simple y puedes hacerlo utilizando tecnologia mundialmente utilizada desde hace cientos de años. Poniendo esto en practica, esta es la silla de ruedas "LFC" que después de algunos años de desarrollo, está ahora en producción. Aqui tienen a un usuario de silla de ruedas, quien sufre de parálisis, en Guatemala, Pueden ver que puede desplazarse por un terreno escabroso. La clave, de nuevo, es que cuando él quiere ir deprisa, sujeta las palancas cerca del eje y utiliza más angulo con cada movimiento y cuando el movimiento se hace mas complicado, solo tiene que deslizar la manos hacia arriba creando un mayor par de fuerza, y disminuyendo la fuerza necesaria para conseguir atravesar el terreno mas difícil. Lo más importante aquí es que la persona es la maquinaria compleja en este sistema. Es la persona la que sube y baja las manos en las palancas por lo que el propio mecanismo es muy simple y puede realizarse con piezas de bicicleta accesibles en cualquier lugar del mundo. Debido a que esas piezas están ampliamente disponibles, son super baratas. Son producidas en ingentes cantidades en China e India y tenemos acceso a ellas en cualquier lugar del mundo, por lo que podemos construir y reparar la silla en cualquier lugar incluso en un pequeño pueblo con el mecánico local, ya que tiene las herramientas, el conocimiento y las piezas disponibles. Cuando se quiere utilizar la silla LFC en interiores, todo lo que hay que hacer es quitar las palancas del tren motriz, guardarlas en los laterales, y se convierte en una silla de ruedas normal que puedes utilizar como cualquier otra, ya que el tamaño es el mismo. Es lo suficientemente estrecha como para atravesar una puerta de tamaño normal, es lo suficientemente baja para encajar debajo de una mesa y es pequeña para que resulte manejable en el baño para que el usuario pueda acercarse al inodoro y sea capaz de sentarse en el como haría con una silla de ruedas convencional. Hay tres puntos en los que me gustaría hacer incapie ya que creo que son la base de este proyecto. El primero es que el producto es viable porque hemos sido capaces de combinar eficazmente rigurosa ingeniería y análisis con un diseño centrado en el usuario teniendo en cuenta los factores sociales y económicos, tan importantes para los usuarios de sillas de ruedas en los países en vías de desarrollo. Como académico en el Instituto Tecnologico de Massachussets e ingeniero mecanico puedo hacer cosas como ver en qué tipo de terreno por el que hay que desplazarse, averiguar cuanta resistencia ofrecerá, ver que piezas hay disponibles, mezclarlas y juntarlas para averiguar que tipo de tren de engranaje se puede utilizar, y después ver la potencia y la fuerza que se puede obtener del tren superior de nuestro cuerpo, para analizar a qué velocidad podremos desplazarnos en esta silla moviendo las manos a lo largo de las palancas. A si que, como un estudiante entusiasmado nuestro equipo creó un prototipo que llevamos a Tanzania, Kenia y Vietnam en el 2008, para descubrir que era pésimo; porque no tuvimos suficiente información de los usuarios. Así que lo probamos con usuarios de sillas de ruedas, con fabricantes que nos dieron su opinión, no solo expresando sus problemas, sino también exponiendo sus soluciones y trabajando conjuntamente volvimos a la mesa de diseño y creamos un nuevo modelo con el que volvimos a África del este en 2009. Resultó funcionar mucho mejor en terreno escabroso que una silla de ruedas convencional aunque todavía no funcionaba bien en interiores ya que era demasiado grande y pesado, difícil de maniobrar. De nuevo, con la opinión de los usuarios, volvimos a la mesa de trabajo y conseguimos un mejor diseño, 9 kilos más ligero, y tan estrecho como una silla de ruedas convencional. Lo probamos en Guatemala y la mejora fue tal que nos llevo , donde estamos ahora, a su producción. Además de ser ingenieros hemos sido capaces de cuantificar los beneficios de rendimiento de nuestra silla LFC. Aquí tienen algunos datos de nuestras pruebas en Guatemala, doinde probamos nuestra LFC en el terreno del pueblo, y recogimos los resultados biomecánicos de los usuarios, su consumo de oxigeno, lo rápido que se desplazan, y cuanta energía emplean en ello, tanto con nuestra silla LFC como con una convencional, y descubrimos que nuestra silla es un 80% más rapida en estos terrenos que una silla tradicional. También es un 40% más eficiente y debido a la ventaja mecánica que se obtiene de las palancas produce un 50% de incremento en el par motor y supone una ayuda real en terreno escabroso. La segunda lección que hemos aprendido es que las limitaciones en el diseño realmente impulsan la innovación. Debido a que teníamos que alcanzar un coste realmente bajo, conseguir que la silla pudiera ser útil en diferentes tipos de terreno a la vez que en interiores y ser lo suficientemente simple para repararla acabamos consiguiendo un producto en esencia nuevo, una innovación en un sector que no ha cambiado en cientos de años. Las ventajas que supone no son sólo aplicables a los países en vías de desarrollo. ¿Por que no también en países como E.E. U.U.? Para ello nos asociamos con Continuum, una empresa de diseño local en Boston para realizar la versión de gama alta apropiada para los países desarrollados, cuyo mercado seria principalmente Estado Unidos y Europa enfocado a compradores de ingresos altos. El último punto que me gustaría resaltar es mi convicción de que este proyecto ha resultado exitoso porque hemos involucrado a todos los inversionistas que han creído en él; que han sido valiosos para desarrollar la tecnología desde la creación de una idea a través de la innovación, validación, comercialización y difusión sabiendo que ese ciclo comienza y termina en los usuarios. Ellos son quienes definen los requisitos tecnológicos y quienes tienen que darnos finalmente el visto bueno diciendo: "Si, efectivamente funciona. Cubre nuestras necesidades". Así, personas como yo en el ámbito académico podemos innovar, analizar y probar, procesar datos y realizar prototipos a nivel experimental. ¿Pero como conseguimos comercializar esos prototipos? Para ello necesitamos expertos en comercialización, como Continuum, lo que nos llevo a crear una ONG para llevar nuestra silla al mercado "Investigación Global de Innovación Tecnológica" y también a asociarnos con un gran fabricante en la India, Industrias Pinnacle, esto nos ha dado capacidad para producir 500 sillas al mes. El primer lote de 200 estará disponible el próximo mes para su envío a la India. Finalmente para acercarnos a la gente a gran escala, nos asociamos con la mayor organización de discapacidad del mundo, "Jaipur Foot". Lo más valioso de este modelo es el poder juntar a todas la partes interesadas que representan a todos los eslabones de la cadena desde la concepción de la idea hasta la implementación en el campo. Ahí es donde sucede la magia. Ahí es donde una persona como yo, un academico puede analizar, probar y crear nueva tecnología y determinar cuantitativamente su rendimiento. Puedes conectar con inversionistas, como los fabricantes, hablar directamente con ellos y hacer uso de su conocimiento en las practicas de fabricación locales y sus clientes; y combinar esas aportaciones con nuestro conocimiento de ingenieria, para crear conjuntamente algo mejor que lo que cualquiera de nosotros podría haber hecho por separado. Así puedes Involucrar también al usuario final en el proceso de diseño, no solo preguntando por sus necesidades, sino preguntándole cómo piensa que pueden conseguirse. Esta es una foto de nuestra ultima prueba de campo en la India, donde tuvimos una tasa de adopción del 90%, que prefirieron el uso de nuestra silla sobre el de una convencional, y esta foto en concreto es de Ashok, que sufre una lesión espinal por una caída de un árbol. Él es sastre, pero desde que sufrió el accidente no ha sido capaz de realizar el trayecto de un kilómetro desde su casa a su tienda en silla de ruedas porque el camino es muy escabroso. Pero el día después de tener nuestra silla, pudo desplazarse ese kilómetro y abrir su tienda, poco después consiguió un contrato para hacer los uniformes del colegio y comenzó a ganar dinero, y pudo mantener a su familia de nuevo. Ashok: "Tu también me animaste a trabajar. Descansé un día en casa y al día siguiente volví a mi tienda. Ahora todo ha vuelto a la normalidad." Amos Winter: Muchas gracias por invitarme hoy.